<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joint Laboratory on Extreme Scale Computing</title>
    <description>The Joint Laboratory for Extreme Scale Computing includes researchers from the French National Institute for Research in Computer Science and Control (INRIA), the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign’s Center for Extreme-Scale Computation, the National Center for Supercomputing Applications, Argonne National Laboratory, Barcelona Supercomputing Center, Julich Supercomputing Center and Riken/AICS. The Joint Lab is part of Parallel@Illinois.
</description>
    <link>https://jlesc.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://jlesc.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>9th JLESC Workshop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The 9th JLESC Workshop will be held at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, USA, from April 15 to 17, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;/events/9th-jlesc-workshop&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more information!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/12/04/9th-workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/12/04/9th-workshop/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Training course on intra-node performance bottlenecks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;JSC is welcoming registrations for the training course “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fz-juelich.de/SharedDocs/Termine/IAS/JSC/EN/courses/2018/intranode-performance-2018.html&quot;&gt;From zero to hero: Understanding and fixing intra-node performance bottlenecks&lt;/a&gt;”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first part of the training course we want to give insights in today’s CPU microarchitecture and apply this knowledge in the hands-on session. As a demonstrator we will use a simple Coulomb solver and improve the code step-by-step. We will start from a basic implementation and advance to an optimized version using hardware features like vectorization to increase performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercises will also contain training on the use of open-source tools to measure and understand the achieved performance. Such optimizations, however, depend heavily on the targeted hardware and should not be part of the algorithmic layer of the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second part we will present a detailed description of possible abstraction layers to hide such hardware-specifics and therefore maintain readability and maintainability. We will also discuss the overhead costs of our introduced abstraction and show compile-time SIMD configurations and corresponding performance results on different platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This advanced course is free of charge and intended for scientists/developers who want to understand performance-critical hardware features of modern CPUs (like SIMD, ILP, caches, out-of-order execution) and utilize these features in their code. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fz-juelich.de/SharedDocs/Termine/IAS/JSC/EN/courses/2018/intranode-performance-2018.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/02/06/training-course-at-jsc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/02/06/training-course-at-jsc/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open JLESC PhD position at JSC</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;JSC has an open position for a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fz-juelich.de/SharedDocs/Stellenangebote/_common/dipldok/d026-2018-jsc.html&quot;&gt;PhD student&lt;/a&gt; in the field of C++ tasking approaches!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jülich Supercomputing Centre is recruiting a PhD student in the field
of computer science with a special focus on C++-based tasking approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is the extension and optimization of our C++
tasking framework for current and future HPC hardware as well as its
application to multigrid methods and the FMM. The project is
embedded into the interdisciplinary research setting of the Joint
Laboratory for Extreme Scale Computing (JLESC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Candidates should hold a university degree in the field of computer science or 
mathematics and should have profound understanding of C++
template metaprogramming, with no fear of numerical methods. Social
competence and good communication skills for collaborative work in and
with interdisciplinary teams are essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project runs for 3 years, for more information, please see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fz-juelich.de/SharedDocs/Stellenangebote/_common/dipldok/d026-2018-jsc.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/02/06/phd-position-at-jsc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/02/06/phd-position-at-jsc/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2018 JSC Guest Student Programme on Scientific Computing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;JSC welcomes applications for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fz-juelich.de/ias/jsc/gsp&quot;&gt;2018 JSC Guest Student Programme on Scientific Computing&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to give students the opportunity to familiarize themselves
with various aspects of scientific computing as early as possible,
the Jülich Supercomputing Centre is once again organizing a
programme for guest students in the 2018 summer vacation. The
programme is supported by CECAM - Centre Europeen de Calcul Atomique 
and IBM. It targets students of science and engineering, computer science and
mathematics who have already completed their first degree but have
not yet finished their master’s course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students will work together with local scientists on topics of
current interest in research and development. Depending on their
previous experience and interests, they will be involved in various
fields of work, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computational Science, Applied Mathematics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modelling and simulation in physics, chemistry and biophysics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Techniques of parallel MD simulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modelling, simulation and data analysis in neuroscience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parallel computational procedures in quantum chemistry and structural mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance evaluation of parallel algorithms in linear algebra&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mathematical modelling, statistics and data mining&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer Architectures, GPU Computing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GPU-computing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High-speed data networks &amp;amp; data management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming models and performance portability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-Performance Computing, Visualization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performance analysis and optimization of parallel programs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming of hierarchical parallel computer systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Distributed applications, interactive control and visualization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virtual reality techniques for visualizing scientific data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme will run for ten weeks from 6 August to 12 October 2018.
During this period JSC grants access to its supercomputers, including
the JURECA installation. The participants should be
familiar with the computational branch of their subject. In addition,
practical experience including at least a good knowledge of programming
with C, C++, Python or Fortran on Linux systems should be present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fz-juelich.de/ias/jsc/gsp&quot;&gt;http://www.fz-juelich.de/ias/jsc/gsp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application deadline: &lt;strong&gt;25 March 2018&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/02/06/gsp-at-jsc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/02/06/gsp-at-jsc/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>UTK becomes Associate Partner</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Starting from January 1, 2018, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utk.edu&quot;&gt;University of Tennessee&lt;/a&gt;, represented by the  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.icl.utk.edu/&quot;&gt;Innovative Computing Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; (ICL) at the University of Tennessee (UTK), becomes new Associate Partner of the JLESC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the University of Tennessee, there are a number of groups working on extreme scale computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Innovative Computing Laboratory aspires to be a world leader in enabling technologies and software for scientific computing. Its vision is to provide high performance tools to tackle science’s most challenging problems and to play a major role in the development of standards for scientific computing in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ICL is a research laboratory in the College of Engineering at the University of Tennessee and serves as the cornerstone laboratory of the Center for Information Technology Research (CITR), one of UT’s nine Centers of Excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome, ICL!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/01/03/icl-associate-partner/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2018/01/03/icl-associate-partner/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>8th JLESC Workshop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The 8th JLESC Workshop will be held at Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC), Barcelona, Spain, from April 17 to 19, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bsc.es/news/events/8th-jlesc-workshop&quot;&gt;official website&lt;/a&gt; for details and registration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2017/11/07/8th-workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2017/11/07/8th-workshop/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>4th JLESC Summer School - Program online</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The fourth JLESC Summer School will be held at NCSA from July 20 to 21, 2017, following the &lt;a href=&quot;/events/7th-jlesc-workshop&quot;&gt;7th JLESC Worksphop&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;/events/4th-jlesc-summer-school&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more information! The program can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncsa.illinois.edu/Conferences/JLESCsummer17/program.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2017/06/13/4th-summer-school/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2017/06/13/4th-summer-school/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>RIKEN AICS HPC Youth Workshop 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;RIKEN AICS HPC Youth Workshop 2016 will take place in Kobe from 28 Nov. to 30 Nov, 
just before the 6th JLESC Workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aics.riken.jp/en/events/161007.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more information!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2016/10/11/youthworkshop-2016/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2016/10/11/youthworkshop-2016/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>6th JLESC Workshop - Call for participation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The 6th JLESC Workshop will be held at RIKEN AICS, Kobe, Japan, from November 30th to December 2nd, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;a href=&quot;/events/6th-jlesc-workshop&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more information!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit proposals for &lt;strong&gt;break-out sessions&lt;/strong&gt; here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/forms/jn9tdkk5dBgUC1XD2&quot;&gt;https://goo.gl/forms/jn9tdkk5dBgUC1XD2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit proposals for &lt;strong&gt;individual talks&lt;/strong&gt; here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/forms/4wzumCB5wpRpLMyL2&quot;&gt;https://goo.gl/forms/4wzumCB5wpRpLMyL2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit &lt;strong&gt;project talks&lt;/strong&gt; here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/forms/1XqT28h1kIGNFIN43&quot;&gt;https://goo.gl/forms/1XqT28h1kIGNFIN43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;DEADLINE: October 7, 2016!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2016/09/21/6th-workshop-calls/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2016/09/21/6th-workshop-calls/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>International funding opportunities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We will gather funding opportunities (e.g. EU or NSF calls) in this and future news post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to support the work of JLESC researchers, the goal is to leverage the effort and multilateral JLESC collaborations for acquiring 3rd party funding, e.g. via EU or NSF projects. 
We will therefore post relevant calls in the news section and encourage everyone to submit further opportunities via their executive director.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, please contact your executive director if you are planning or about to submit a JLESC-related proposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, we start with an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=503394&quot;&gt;overview&lt;/a&gt; of NSF calls. In particular, the SAVI call, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=504756&amp;amp;org=NSF&quot;&gt;Science Across Virtual Institutes&lt;/a&gt;, is relevant for JLESC researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://jlesc.github.io/news/2016/09/05/funding-opportunities/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://jlesc.github.io/news/2016/09/05/funding-opportunities/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
